All right.
This is the concluding lecture for Financial Markets.
And in this lecture, I
want to, I titled this lecture,
Finding Your Purpose in a World of Financial Capitalism.
But I just want to give
a lot of summary thoughts about the
course and about your place in the world of
business and finance.
The major textbook for this
course was by Fibozzi et al.
And it gave you a lot of detailed information about
financial markets and institutions.
Did you like it?
I'm getting approval, I guess.
I put you through something,
because I thought you have to
know that material.
Finances.
Like a letter.
Like a language.
What is a language?
There's a lot of jargon.
And behind the jargon are concepts.
And so, I wanted you to immerse yourself in that.
I also assigned my manuscript
for my new book, which is
tentatively entitled, Finance and the Good Society.
I'm still not sure that that will be.
I'm not sure that that will be the final title.
Some of you have been
offering me suggested titles, and I
appreciate that.
You can never know what the
title of a book will be before
you publish it, because someone else can always grab
the title, and then you've got to change it.
So.
But that book was about, I
wanted to see, Fibozzi is more
about all of the language
of finance, and all of the
technical details.
I wanted to supplement it
with something about the purpose of
all this, and how it fits into our lives.
So, it's not done yet, as
you may be well aware in reading
it.
My apologies.
But I benefit from interacting with
you about it, and it's a
dynamic thing.
So I have a number of themes.
They're all just kind of random thoughts about the major
things in this course.
But I mean, I'm really thinking
this time about the kind of
tools we've learned about.
Tools that are particularly useful for people who
specialize in finance.
But I think this almost
should be a required course for
everyone.
Maybe I'm just too enthusiastic about it.
But I think it's a good thing.
I mean, knowing, the way
things get done in our society
is through financial arrangements.
And too many people talk in vague terms.
How are we going to make something happen?
And finance is about that.
So that's why I think
this course should be, there should
be more students taking it than are.
I also said that I think
that finance is not a purpose, it's
a tool.
And that you should be building
your life around some kind of
purpose.
There's a million different purposes, so that's something
for you to create in your own mind.
But that's where the meaning of life comes from.
So another thing I've emphasized in this course is
that finance is like engineering.
So you have to design it, you
have to design it, you have to
design it.
And once something is designed
and it works, it gets copied
all over the world.
So you all have learned how to drive a car.
Is anyone here who hasn't driven a car?
I won't ask for it.
No one raised their hand.
So you have to know a
little bit about mechanics, right, to
drive a car.
Maybe not too much.
But ultimately, what I wanted to
do in this course is maybe
not teach you how to build a car.
But how to drive a truck.
Okay?
Something big and powerful.
And get you beyond the simple things.
So finance, what does it do?
It does really important things.
It helps allocate scarce resources.
It incentivizes people to do good work.
And it manages risks.
And this is what makes for the developed world.
It's a great tool.
It's a great tool to help people.
It's a great tool to
help people in the developed world
that we have now.
Another theme of this
course is about information technology,
which is something that's rapidly expanding.
I don't have to tell you that.
But I think that it
will change the world of finance.
The last 50 years have shown tremendous changes.
The next 50 years will show even more dramatic changes.
So.
All right.
Anyway, more specifically, I have seven themes that I want
to cover in today's lecture.
The first one is just about the morality of finance.
I've been talking about this here and again.
But let me say a little
bit more about that in concluding.
My second theme is hopelessness.
There's a tendency for people
to think that at some level,
because of the world's problems,
it's all hopeless anyway.
I don't think it is.
Well, I'll come out to tell
you what I mean by that.
Then thirdly, I just want
to say something about financial theory.
Then fourth, to come back to
another theme, which is wealth and poverty,
which I've talked about a lot.
Then the world of the next century.
And I think one trend we'll
see is the democratization of finance.
That finance will become much more
of an integral part of our lives
in a new information technology enriched world.
And then lastly, I'll say something about your career,
whether it's in finance
or in something completely different.
But I'm thinking that a good chance
it has something to do with finance.
Okay.
So, let me start, though, with
the first thing, which is about morality.
Actually, the two optional readings I have
on this part of the reading list
are both about morality.
And one is the book by
Unger called Living High and Letting Die.
I think it's a dramatically well-written book.
But on the first page of
the book, he refers you to UNICEF.
Actually, his book was written before the web got popular.
The book is 1994, I think.
He could have referred to the web.
But he gave the address.
UNICEF is the United Nations,
what does the I stand for?
Children's Educational Fund.
But what's the I?
Can someone tell me?
They don't actually emphasize what it's spelled out.
It's the United Nations Fund for Children of the World.
And that's their website.
So, he opens the book by saying,
why don't you get out your checkbook
right now and mail in $100 to unicef.org,
because the estimate as of 1996 is
that UNICEF can save a child's life
for $3.
So, you will save the lives
of 33 children for your $100 check.
How can they do that?
How can they save a life?
I think maybe he's referring
to things like vaccination programs,
things that are really cheap
that some children are not getting.
And so, statistically, you can
save a child's life for $3.
So, he says, write out a check.
But, of course, I can tell you what to do.
And that is, just, get lost in the world.
Log on to that and get out your credit card.
And I don't know if you can save
33 lives with $100, but maybe you can.
So, when I first read the book, I
thought about that, and then I turned the page.
Most of us do.
And I realized later that I, a month
later, that I'd never written out a $100 check.
So, I finally did.
And I went on to unicef.org, and
I gave exactly $100, as he called it.
And I was told for.
Then I started, you know, that
was thought-provoking to think about that.
Because why did I stop at $100?
Why is it that most of us don't do that?
There are intellectual defenses we have.
We think of ourselves as good people.
But if you were to see a dying child,
right, you would emotionally be driven to do something.
If there was something you could do, right?
But somehow, when they're not visible to us,
we don't take action to make them visible.
What the book consists of, Unger's book consists of, is an
analysis of all the excuses we give for not doing it.
For not doing that sort of thing.
So, living our comfortable lives
and letting other people die.
And I think it's really an interesting book.
Because it is referring to a paradox of human behavior.
I think of this as at
the juncture of philosophy and psychology.
And now those two departments are starting to,
I understand, I'm not in either one of them,
but are starting to come together.
Because they're realizing that philosophical
issues are related to psychological issues.
So, somehow the human spirit is
very empathetic and sympathetic in certain dimensions.
Not so in others.
So, you know, when you read his book, you
get a sense of meaninglessness or loss of purpose.
It's not entirely comfortable to read it.
He has a lot of examples of moral dilemmas.
I don't mean to find fault with his book.
But when I think further about it, it seems that maybe
the book is a bit circumscribed by the kind of moral dilemmas
that he poses.
In some sense, moral dilemmas are, it's almost like there's
a moral imperative for us to take action, to do things.
That's sort of what he's getting at.
But there's almost a moral imperative
to be entrepreneurial to do things.
And, you know, I mentioned before,
Paul Allen, who was one
of the top people in Microsoft,
who made so much money and squandered
some of it, apparently, on conspicuous consumption.
But on the other hand,
gives a billion dollars to charity.
So, it seems to me that this,
let's not conclude that people who
don't write the $100 check are evil.
Let's think of the many dimensionalities of morality.
So, the other book I had on this
part of the course was by William Graham Sumner.
And it was written over 100 years earlier, 1883, called,
What the Social Classes Owe Each Other.
And, you know, I think,
you know, it's a great book.
And Sumner was actually Yale's first real economist.
Interesting person.
He was hired, he graduated Yale College in 1863.
And he was hired by Yale
as a tutor in mathematics in 1866.
And became interested in economics and sociology.
He has the distinction of being the first
American professor to teach a course called sociology.
And in those days, there wasn't the distinction
between the social sciences that there is now.
So, he could teach both sociology and economics.
So, in his book, I think he started a
Yale tradition of conservative economics that lasted until the 1940s.
And then Yale kind of
drifted more toward the liberal end.
But he writes anyway in 1883,
Is it wicked to be rich?
Is it mean to be a capitalism, a capitalist?
And he says, first of all, it seems, you
know, if capitalists are just richer than other people.
Yes, where is the drawing
dividing line when someone is rich?
So, is it wicked to be above that line?
But where do you draw the line?
And if you learn from Unger, maybe we're all wicked.
Because anyone who doesn't write a
$100 check every day to UNICEF,
when children are dying around the world, is wicked.
But what Sumner is saying, you know, it seems to
be a theme that survives the centuries in favor of capitalists.
I'll quote Sumner,
The great gains of a
great capitalist in a modern state
must be put under the head of wages of superintendents.
Anyone who believes that any
great enterprise of an industrial character
can be started without labor
must have little experience of life.
Let anyone try to get a
railroad built or to start a factory
and win reputation for its products.
And he will find what obstacles must be overcome,
what risks must be taken,
what perseverance and courage are necessary.
So,
I don't know that I entirely agree with Sumner.
But he has a point that
part of our morality
is to do good for the world
by doing things like set up railroads
or Microsoft.
And the kind of activities that that entails will
create opportunities for conspicuous consumption.
But not for the people.
And I don't necessarily make that the
defining characteristic of someone who does it.
Nobody is perfect.
And it's hard to judge people ultimately.
But it seems to me that
there's almost a moral imperative to entrepreneurship.
So,
let me go on to the second
theme that I said I would talk about.
And that is hopelessness.
A lot of people from
their education get the idea that
ultimately, there's nothing we can really do.
This is one of Unger's talks about
rationalizations we give for not being moral.
And he calls it futility is a rationalization.
Ultimately, there's always going to
be starving people in the world.
And, you know, I can try to help this child,
but something is going to get him later.
And so, there's no point.
If you have that kind of futility, sense of futility,
it can justify any amount of hedonism.
But I think that the classic article that
lends most people to that sense of futility,
and I assume you know about this already,
but it's Malthus, 1798.
His essay on, well, the title of it was
Essay on the Principle of Population.
So, Thomas Malthus wrote about the population problem.
It was such a celebrated essay that
he went through six editions of it.
But I'm going to quote from
the first edition just to remind you.
He said in 1798,
Population, when unchecked,
increased in a geometrical ratio
and subsistence for man in an arithmetical ratio.
You know, so the population
growth follows an exponential growth curve.
He says geometrical, but it goes like that.
Whereas he said, at best,
the increase in our ability to produce is linear,
or he calls that arithmetical.
And so,
population will run off with all of our resources.
There's nothing we can do.
Population will continue to put pressure on our resources.
He says, I'm quoting again from his 1798 essay,
Population, when unchecked, goes on
doubling itself every 25 years.
In the next, if you go through two 25-year periods,
where there was no check on population growth,
it is impossible, I'm quoting him,
to suppose that the produce could be quadrupled.
It would be contrary to all
our knowledge of the qualities of land.
Then he comes now to his dismal law of economics.
He didn't call it that.
I'm quoting, but I will quote him.
No possible form of society
could prevent the almost constant action of misery
upon a great part of mankind,
if in a state of inequality,
and upon all, if all were equal.
So, that the natural state of humankind
is bordering on starvation and dying.
And the force of his argument was quite profound,
because it was hard to argue against him
that there's nothing you can do about it.
That's just it.
And all the theorizing of people
can only result in a world
where more people are suffering and dying.
If you want to think more about this,
I suggest you might go to Robert Wyman,
who is a professor here at Yale,
on Open Yale,
which means it's another of these
courses open on the Internet.
Has a course called
Global Problems of Population Growth,
where he spends a whole semester
thinking about the Malthusian problem.
One thing that he talks about in that course
is that there's a popular sense that
the population problem is not so bad anymore,
because many countries have
introduced birth control policies.
I mean, notably China has a one-child policy, supposedly.
It's not really a one-child policy.
It's not enforced that well.
It's more like a two-child policy,
and people have even more than that.
But other countries, India,
and certain regions of India have made great progress,
we're told, in birth control.
But still, despite that,
Wyman estimates that the world adds
a billion people every 12 years.
So, that's a problem.
And our resources are limited.
So, the problem is that
people are crowding into the cities,
because there's no room for them on the land.
They're trying to get an education
to push themselves ahead,
but the sheer numbers of people
make it impossible for them all to get ahead.
So, I suggest that you might take his course.
It's a problem that people don't want
to get up to.
So, I'm sounding very dismal here.
But actually, I think that the problem
is not as bad as it may seem.
This is my take on it.
I tend to be a realist about these things.
We have a population problem.
It's going to be with us.
But hey, it's been with us forever,
going all the way back in history.
So, it's a tough world that we live in,
where the human race is naturally procreating
and naturally creating population pressures
and conflicts that lead to wars and famines.
We've been going through a good run
in the last few centuries,
but it's growing.
I don't know when the end,
it's not an end,
when we're going to see more severe problems.
That just seems to be right and inevitable.
But I think that that doesn't mean,
I think that the weakest part of Malthus' argument
is the last step, saying that it's necessarily
a dismal world that results.
I wanted to put the
bright side on Malthus' dismal law.
And that is, most of the time, everyone's fine.
In the world, most people, you know,
it's famines and wars are intermittent events.
That reduce population.
Between those big events,
pretty much everyone is doing all right.
So, I mean, maybe it's
not as bad as you think.
You know, you might get killed in a war someday,
but you enjoy life until that happens.
I mean, that's very basic, but I think it's true.
But moreover, I think that there's
a lot that we can do
to make life better,
even in the context of the dismal law,
and accepting the dismal law.
And I think that civilization is improving,
so that life is better,
even though there are population pressures.
And that's why I think there's a, you know,
maybe I'm saying the obvious here,
but I want to say it anyway,
that there are plenty of purposes and goals
that people can fulfill,
even taking as given Malthus' dismal law.
So, I talked last period,
about nonprofit and charity,
and government as well.
There are a lot of
people who are doing specific things
to make the world respond better
to the dismal law of Malthus.
And I wanted to mention certain examples,
just to make this clear.
I think that there's work being done
by governments of the world.
There's also work being done by individuals
who don't need government.
They set up their own organizations.
So, I was specifically talking about the environment.
This is what's being threatened by population growth.
And so, there are many foundations
that deal with the environment.
I'll just mention a few.
The Nature Conservancy,
the World Wildlife Fund,
the Wildlife Conservation Society,
and there's specialized ones called,
like African Wildlife Foundation,
the Jane Goodall Institute,
the Dian Fossey Gorilla Fund.
You know, you think the gorillas out there are wild,
but there's finance and support.
They've collected money.
Someone is managing an endowment for the gorillas.
Okay?
This is creative finance.
You know, a part of the problem with,
you think about what's happening
with the population pressures of the world.
And is it bad or not?
Well, in some sense, it's good.
Having, you know, 10 billion people on the world
would just make it for a more interesting place, right?
There'd be more arts and sciences
and fun things to do.
Eventually, we're going to colonize the moon and Mars,
and there's going to be fun trips to do.
So, I don't know if it's a bad world
that we're coming into.
Even if there are conflicts.
But part of, you know,
I think there are specific problems
with that world.
And one of them is the extinction of species.
You think about that.
You know, we're destroying habitat for species,
and they're going to be gone forever.
So, but the thing is that those kinds of problems
are problems that have sort of business solutions.
And I wanted to talk about one particular foundation.
I don't know if you've heard of it.
It's a non-profit.
And I'll just give this as an example.
The Nature Conservancy.
It was founded in 1951 in the United States,
but it now operates in 30 countries.
Its total assets are 5.6 billion,
which makes it the third largest charity
in the United States.
And they have a principle of conservation by design.
The idea is, our purpose
is to prevent extinction of species.
Because extinction is forever.
You know, these species have taken hundreds of millions
of years to evolve.
They get wiped out, they're gone.
As far as we know, they're gone forever.
What they do is, they get scientists who specialize
in environment and biology, and they say,
which species are endangered, and what can we really do
to prevent their extinction?
And one thing that the scientists have been telling them
is that you have to preserve habitat for species,
and you have to do it with purpose and clarity.
What do these animals need?
Some of them are migratory, for example,
and they migrate over long distances.
So, you have to preserve a migratory route
and stopping places along the way for them.
So, it has to be done well.
So, the Nature Conservancy believes also that the way
to protect habitat is to buy
land and put up fences around,
have to keep people out,
and then have a forest manager
run it, so that the
species will have a good life.
So, they have to do it.
And they say that they have 500,000 square kilometers
of land that they've bought around the world.
I calculated that there's 150 million square kilometers
of land on the Earth.
So, they have one-third of
1% of the world's land protected
by their charity.
Now, that might seem small,
but that's a big difference, right?
Because if it's the last thing they have,
that's a big difference.
Because if it's the last habitat, that might be enough
to keep a lot of species diversity going.
So, that's an example of what, this is really finance.
We have portfolio managers managing portfolio
and properties of land with a good purpose.
And, you know, that's why I say the moral dilemmas
are not so simple.
You could take a job managing a portfolio for one
of these foundations.
Peter Unger, in his book, is talking about, always about,
you know, would you save a
child who fell in the water
or something like that.
But that's not the kind of
moral dilemmas that we really face.
That an energetic intellect would find.
The moral dilemma is to
prevent big, bad things from happening.
And that takes a sort of entrepreneurship and big
thinking to manage.
Another thought I had in this context is about wars.
I was saying that population
pressures are a fact of life.
And I'm skeptical that anyone will change the basic
nature of the situation.
But I wanted in this context to emphasize that financial
arrangements are capable of enduring and surviving wars
and catastrophes.
I wanted particularly to make
it clear that there's a tendency
for people to think that
finance is something that the government
runs.
You can easily get that impression, because when you
go into finance, the first thing
you have to do is get licensed.
You have to file some papers
with either the government or a
government-approved organization.
And then you will find there's
a whole list of laws and
regulations that you have to memorize, and forms that have
to be filed with government agencies, and permissions to be
granted.
So, it sounds like this is just the government.
But I think that's the wrong view.
I think that you should
think of finance as people making
arrangements with other people.
And governments are helpful, and they enforce contracts, but
they don't determine them.
And in particular, I wanted to
give you a few examples that
clarify this.
What do you think happened after World War II?
After World War I, with financial arrangements.
Germany lost the war.
People were really angry with Germany.
In the Versailles Conference after World War I, Germany was
made to pay huge reparation payments, payments that some
people thought were so heavy
that the country will never be
able to do it.
What do you think they did to financial contracts?
You know, Germany was at its knees.
People thought they were evil.
Many people thought they were evil.
Well, there was talk about taking away people who owned
stocks or bonds.
Let's just confiscate them and tell
them, you know, you were in
the wrong country at the wrong time.
Tough on you.
But they talked about doing
it, but they didn't do it.
The reparations were obligations of the German government.
And they were paid by taxing people.
And they taxed people in an equitable – they didn't
actually pay them, by the way.
The skeptics were right.
Germany never was able to pay the reparations.
But it tried to pay
them by taxing people, not by
confiscating.
Because ultimately, when it came down to it, they thought,
well, you know, Germans are all different.
And some of them supported the
war, and some of them didn't.
And some of them saved all
their lives, and they've got a
big amount of money.
So, let's not confiscate their shares.
So, they didn't.
That's my first example.
Second example.
Iran.
Remember, it was ruled by the
Shah of Iran, who is a secular
ruler, hereditary ruler of Iran, overthrown by a
people's Islamic revolution and the Ayatollah Khomeini
became the spiritual authority for the new country, became
much more Islamic.
All right.
So, what do you think
happened to financial contracts in Iran?
In particular, the Iranian government under the Shah had a
social security system, and they were paying to government
employees pensions.
So, what do you think the Ayatollah did?
Guy's working all his life
for the Shah, we've overthrown the
Shah, do you still get your pension?
What do you think?
They did.
They didn't cancel.
I think it's like common sense.
You come in, you are a totally different government.
Now, you're an Islamic, a radical Islamic government.
Now, I don't say that they
won't do some things that you
don't like, but they see the basic financial contracts and
they preserve them.
The other example I'll give is
South Africa, and that is in
1994, the white apartheid government was replaced by a
government that was elected by
the black majority in South Africa.
So, what do you think
happened to their pensions or their
insurance?
Were they confiscated?
No.
I think that this is a principle in history.
Now, I can give other examples,
of course, where things went badly.
Vladimir Lenin wasn't so kind
to stockholders in Russia after
this Russian revolution.
Lazaro Cardenas in Mexico nationalized the oil industry.
Mao Zedong, you know who he
is in China, not kind to
capitalists.
Mohammad Mossadegh in Iran nationalized the oil industry.
Gamal Abdel Nasser in Egypt nationalized the oil industry.
And then, in India, there
was a nationalized, wide range of
industries.
Even in India, Indira Gandhi did widespread nationalizations
that were effectively confiscations.
Even the United States has,
in some sense, been involved in
those sorts of things.
After World War II, the
United States was not going to
confiscate wealth of wealthy people in general.
But in Japan, there were these wealthy families that were
going to maintain the industries, called Zaibatsu.
These were the family-owned businesses that dominated Japan
before World War II.
The big four, Mitsubishi, Yasuda, who else?
What are the, Mitsui, and what am I thinking of?
It's not in my notes.
But these big, wealthy families were thought to have
supported the war and made Japan into more radical than
it would have been.
So, there was a lot of
U.S. thinking that we had to break
up the Zaibatsu.
So, what the United States
did is force these families to
convert their holdings of
industry in Japan into yen-denominated
government bonds.
And then, the Japanese government had a huge
hyperinflation and wiped them out.
So, it wasn't actually a confiscation.
The U.S. government didn't deliberately confiscate the
wealth of the Zaibatsu.
But they effectively did that.
By the way, we still
have Zaibatsu in Japan, but they're
not owned by those families anymore.
The same industrial conglomerates still survive.
So, third topic I was saying
I would talk about is, maybe I'll
be brief about this, the importance of financial theory.
So, I'm an advocate of two seemingly disparate things.
And you know this from this course.
One of them is mathematical finance.
We spent some time on it,
but not very much, because there's
another course that's also on Open Yale that John D.
John Akopoulos has on mathematical finance.
But the other side of it
is behavioral finance, which is a
particular passion of mine.
And behavioral finance is the application of psychology and
other social sciences to finance.
And I think that the two actually work together
symbiotically.
And we consider them together.
Some people in mathematical finance are very opposed to
behavioral finance, because it kind of muddles their world.
But in fact, I think they should consider it their
salvation, because without behavioral finance, they're
kind of bordering on irrelevant.
You have to consider things in
a broader context and think of
the interruptions and problems that are caused.
And I think that's the way to do it.
So, I said the next topic
I would talk about today is, I've
already been talking about it
a bit, is about wealth and
poverty.
It seems to me it's fundamentally connected with
our thoughts about finance.
Because, you know, I referred to this problem before, that
people think that people who go into finance are money
grubbers.
They want to make money.
They don't have human feelings.
They want to make money
out of feelings or something like
that.
And there's also this sense
that we're living in a world
that's increasingly plutocratic, that the wealthy people are
controlling the world.
That was a theme that took
a lot of impetus in the 19th
century with Karl Marx, who said exactly that.
And in some sense, it's coming
back, maybe in not such an
extreme form.
So, Jacob Hacker, who's in our political science department,
and Paul Pearson, who's at Stanford University, have a
new book that just came out called, Winner Take All
Politics.
And that book is about politics.
And the book is about, they
have a claim in that book that
the world is getting more polarized by the political
power of financial institutions.
Basically, they have something they call the 30 Years War.
What's the 30 Years War?
You might think it's something that happened in the 17th
century.
Not for them.
The 30 Years War is the
war against the people of the world
fought by the financial community.
And the 30 Years War is the
war against the people of the world
fought by the halls of Congress and Parliament, by lobbying.
So, they argue that the companies have gotten more and
more sophisticated in lobbying governments to fulfill their
ambitions.
And so, the income inequality that we're seeing increasing,
particularly in the United States, but elsewhere in the
world, is a consequence of this.
And so, much of the literature
on income inequality says it has
something to do with the information revolution, which is
eliminating jobs for low-income people, and the increasing
importance of education, which
rewards college graduates at the
expense of uneducated people.
But they say that the
real increase in inequality has not
been between high school graduates and college
graduates.
It's between the whole population and the top tenth of
a percent.
There is this small community
of super rich people that are
developing, who are very adept at lobbying governments.
This is a trend that's developing.
So, well, I think, to some extent, they are probably
right.
I think maybe they overstate
that, but I think it's a
concern.
But I think it's a concern.
I think that we do have democratic institutions, and
we can respond to that.
I think maybe they overstate it, because I think that
I've met billionaires in my life,
and I have a sense that
they are not, I guess they have, sometimes they might
have, I haven't met enough of them to make generalities
about billionaires, but maybe they
have a little bit of a
self-serving mentality.
But in some sense, they seem not to care.
They don't want to be viewed as evil.
They want to be, a lot
of what drove them to become
billionaires was a sense that
they would be a benefactor of
some sort.
And so, they're ready to give it away.
Anyway, that may be a casual impression.
But one thing that angers people about wealth is the
tendency of wealthy people to build monuments to themselves.
So, I was thinking of that
when I was at the J.P. Morgan
Library in New York.
And also, there's something called the Metropolitan Club,
which is another building that he built to himself.
This huge mansion in Manhattan that he built.
And I was thinking, is J.P. Morgan evil?
I mean, people are starving
in the world, and he's building
a mansion for himself.
But then I reflected further.
Here, I am having dinner in his house.
Here, I am having dinner in his mansion.
He's gone.
And is it really so
bad in the scheme of things?
So, it comes down to how you,
I guess you can view it in
different ways.
You can view J.P. Morgan as
a great success, who was a
great businessman, who ended up helping the world.
Or you can view him as a selfish monument builder.
But so, his life overlapped
with Karl Marx, that I told
you about.
But one of Karl Marx's themes
was that the system is unfair,
that some people have capital.
And I think that's the
essence of his book Das Kapital.
Some people have capital, and
they are wealthy as a result,
and they will continue to
be wealthy, and they'll make their
children wealthy as a result.
I actually have a quote from Karl Marx.
It is not because he is
a leader of industry that a man
is a capitalist.
On the contrary, he is a
leader of industry because he is a
capitalist.
The leadership of industry is an attribute of capital, just
as in feudal times, the functions of capital were not
the same.
The functions of general and judge were attributes of landed
property.
That comes from his book, Kapital, in 19th century.
So, Marx thought that ownership of
capital was like a key to
the good life, and that the population was excluded from
that.
But I'm going to come back to the democratization of
capitalism.
I think capitalism is a very important class in the
world of finance.
But it seems like capitalism, it isn't essential to
capitalism that some social class dominates capital.
We can have a capitalism that
is divided up among, that is
more of people's.
It belongs to people, and it's not a privileged class.
So, I think that's what I'm
going to talk about, is my
concern.
You know, Marx was impressed, I
think I may have said this
before, he was impressive because he read emerging
sociology.
And the sociology of his
day was beginning to recognize that
people do form themselves into
social classes, and they have a
sense of loyalty to others in their social class.
But I think that, you know,
anything he said is of limited
relevance today.
It was always of limited relevance.
And it's wrong in many ways.
But I'm thinking of the works of another important thinker,
Robert K. Merton, who is a sociologist at Columbia.
He is the father of
the Robert Merton economist, who helped
develop option theory.
But Robert K. Merton referred to what he called the
cosmopolitan class.
So, he was looking at social classes.
He picked a small town in
the United States and interviewed a
lot of people, and was trying to understand their class
structure, you know, who do
you identify with, who are you
loyal with.
And he was a deep thinker,
I think, and looked at what
really seemed to separate people.
And he decided that in
this little town, that there were
really two classes of people.
He called them cosmopolitans and locals.
So, the cosmopolitans had a very different world view.
They tended to not care about
what's going on in their town.
They would talk about national or international things.
You know, you'd listen to what they say.
They were focused outside.
They thought the town was irrelevant.
And it tended to have maybe higher level positions.
The locals were people, though,
who would talk all about their
town, and they would talk about people they know.
They seemed to value their connections within the town.
And when you asked for opinions
about the local town, the locals
would tend to give almost loving expressions.
This is a great town.
We have great people here.
And the cosmopolitans would act totally indifferent.
And they don't know anybody.
They don't know who's the head
of the fire department, or who
holds the, maybe they know
the principal of the school, because
they may have their kid in the school.
But beyond that, they don't know anything about their town.
So, Merton wrote that over 50 years ago.
I have a sense that it's developing further, this split.
Between cosmopolitans and locals.
And it's developing on a world scale.
There is now a world cosmopolitan class.
And with increased communications, we're
kind of split that way.
So, people around the world
who are learning to speak English,
well, that's the world language.
People who travel around the world.
And people who are finance savvy.
And people who are also
are developing into a social class.
And I think that there are animosities and conflicts.
But it's a little bit
harder to have, because the cosmopolitans
are so scattered, and they're relatives of us.
So, it's not as intense a social contrast.
But I think that the animosities that we are
feeling now, have to do with the fact that
cosmopolitans know and understand finance.
And they have lawyers and advisors.
The rest of the population feels excluded from that.
So, that brings us to what
I said was the democratization of finance.
And this is a theme of
my own, that I've been emphasizing.
So, the democratization of finance is
sort of trying to make it
move beyond the cosmopolitan class.
So, cosmopolitans know how to get
things done, how to raise capital.
And they know how to manage their
risks, so they don't get into trouble.
Inequality is substantially due to
a failure to manage risks.
So, in the, right?
I mean, some inequality is due to fundamental things,
like someone is talented and can make more money.
But it's also due to
random things that are not controlled.
Notably, in the current financial crisis, we
saw a huge drop in home values.
And we saw people who bought
homes at the top of the market,
and then they find that their mortgages
are worth more than their homes are.
And so, they have a negative net worth.
They're in trouble.
They would be bankrupt.
Maybe they're not bankrupt yet, but they're verging on that.
They're very unhappy.
This was a failure, I think,
of bringing finance to the people.
So, it's not democratizing finance.
We haven't finished democratizing finance.
So, you know, it's kind
of chaotic, the way things work,
for most people.
Most people who, A, do not have a lawyer.
B, do not have a financial advisor.
C, do not have an accountant.
All right?
Or maybe they go to
some, you know, storefront taxpaying service.
But that's as far as they go.
And these people make a mess of their lives.
So, for example, we have laws
that allow people to go bankrupt
and wipe off their debts.
All you have to do, if
you are in trouble, financial trouble,
is go to a lawyer and say,
can you help me file for Chapter 7 bankruptcy?
I'd like to wipe out all my debts.
But usually, you have to
have $1,000 to pay the lawyer
to help you do this.
And these people can't get it together to do that.
So, what happens?
What happens to this typical person who's uneducated,
has gotten deeply in debt?
What do you think happens?
Do they ever declare bankruptcy?
No.
What do they do?
They stop answering the phone, because they're getting these
dunning calls from creditors.
And so, the creditors then, it's called informal bankruptcy.
They will go to court and
ask the judge to allow them to
garnish the wages of the person who
won't pay and won't answer the phone.
So, they'll take another deduction from the person
who won't pay and the person's paycheck eventually,
the person never figures it out.
His paycheck just went down.
He's paying off his debt.
What a mess.
But that's because of the failure of financial institutions
to handle things well.
So, Elizabeth Warren, who is at, I mentioned her before,
at the Harvard Law School,
has written a couple of books
about the problems that people face.
And it's a testimony to the success of our democratic
government that she managed to
persuade Dodd and Frank to put
it in her bill, in their bill.
The Consumer Financial Protection Bureau, which would
create a government agency that would try to limit the
abuse of lower-income, less-educated people.
We were hoping that she would
be made head of her bureau,
but it turns out that she
is only acting, I don't know what
her exact title is, transitioning into finding head
for the bureau, because the lobbyists that I told you
about representing credit card or mortgage industries are
adamantly opposed to seeing her.
They're not seeing her put
on as head of the bureau.
So, it looks like it's politically impossible to put
her in charge of it.
But she's at least involved
in helping pick the person who
would make that happen.
So, I think these are nice steps forward.
But I wrote a book, let me
just mention my own book, in 2008,
called Subprime Solution.
And so, I was trying to think of the future.
Again, I'm trying to think creatively and expansively
without thinking punitively, as Elizabeth Warren seems often
to do.
Her view tends to be that
there are exploiters who need to be
regulated.
But I'm thinking that maybe there's something positive we
can do.
So, I have various ideas.
Also, I had, this was 2008,
I also had another book, New
Financial Order in 2003.
I'm getting on toward 10 books now in my life.
I'm having trouble remembering which one is which.
I was just commenting to my wife.
It's a little bit of a problem.
But somewhere in these books, one
of the ideas I had actually
it's in New Financial Order, is for livelihood insurance.
That would help protect, this
is a financial institution that
would protect people's livelihoods.
I viewed it as an expansion
of something that we got already
called disability insurance.
In fact, it's been offered
by the government in the United
States as part of the Social Security system.
But it handles certain
insurance against certain specific kinds
of risks to livelihoods.
Namely, health risks.
If you become paralyzed, if
you become mentally ill, any of
those things that a doctor
can attest to is insured already.
Very important, because things like
that happen to people, and
they can't earn a living anymore.
And it happens to young people.
And so, we have private insurance.
The government has taken over part of disability insurance,
but there's also private disability insurance.
But none of this covers the biggest threats to people's
livelihoods.
Most threats to livelihoods are not due to medical events.
It's economic events that make
you, you know, you're 40 years
old, you've trained for,
let's say, nuclear engineering, okay?
And then we have the Fukushima or the Sendai disasters.
And then suddenly, no government
of the world wants to build
nuclear plants anymore.
So, here you are, you're
40 years old, you're reaching your
prime.
You would normally be making a
good high income, but now it's
useless.
No fault of your own.
This is a risk that you cannot
now insure, and it's part of the
thing that contributes to inequality.
And so, I think that we can insure those things.
And in the future, as finance
develops, these are some of the
missions that we have to do.
Another thing is home equity insurance that I mentioned
before, that the credit card.
I mentioned before that the
crisis was caused by a failure
to insure against home price risk.
I've been working on trying to get home equity insurance
started.
Some of my colleagues at
Yale, Will Goetzman and Barry Nailbuff
particularly, have actually created an insurance policy that
would insure homes against price declines in the city of
Syracuse, New York.
But it didn't really take off,
so this is still not happening
yet.
But here's the idea.
You can buy insurance against your home burning down.
That goes back 300 years.
But how often do homes burn down?
Not very often.
What's the real risk that you face?
It's the loss of economic value of a home.
And so, that is not insured anywhere in the world.
Why not?
We could insure it.
I think these are things that would, developing home equity
insurance or livelihood insurance would be positive
steps.
I have one more example from this book, Subprime Solution.
Something I call a continuous workout mortgage.
Okay.
In the financial crisis today,
right now, there's a lot of
people who are on the
verge of defaulting on their mortgages.
Right now, there are 2.5 million households that are on
the verge of defaulting on their mortgages.
Haven't yet, but they are
at risk of defaulting and being
thrown out of their houses.
So, that's something like close to 10 million people.
Big time event.
Why is it that they're being thrown out?
Well, because their home value has dropped.
Maybe they're unemployed, their income has dropped.
We still have 8.8% unemployment.
And they can't pay their mortgage.
So, they think it's futile, because they're paying a debt
that is bigger than their wealth.
And so, maybe they don't feel
in a very good mood about it.
They go back to the mortgage
lender and ask for a workout.
And the mortgage lender typically says no.
The government has done a
sequence of programs to try to
encourage the servicers of mortgages to do workouts.
That means lower their payments or somehow make it easier.
But it's been disappointing.
They haven't succeeded in
getting cooperation on these programs.
It's one of the big tragedies of the financial crisis.
So, what I propose is that we should think forward.
I don't know how we
can solve this mess right now.
But think about in the future
having mortgages that have a pre-planned workout.
And the workout would lower the cost of,
lower the payment on the mortgage continuously.
The other problem with workouts is,
even when people get a workout on their mortgage,
they default anyway, because things get even worse later.
You've got one workout, you go back and say,
I'd like another workout.
They say, you've got to be kidding.
Anyway, the government, like the HAMP program that
the Obama administration has promoted,
has only one workout for each.
And that's for families.
So, I think they should be continuous and automatic.
And they don't require anyone to apply for a workout.
Okay.
So, how much time do I have?
I think I'll move to my last subject,
which is your career.
Because you are young people.
And you may be wondering what you want to do.
So, I think that,
I think maybe I've reflected on this before.
You probably feel that you want to do something important.
And you want a sort of perfect career.
Something that tells a story,
makes a story of your life.
And ultimately serves for good causes.
But it's, when you read Unger,
you don't get an inspiration like that, right?
You get, he says, write
a check right now to UNICEF.
Well, I can do that.
But does that, you know, it seems unrewarding,
just to give to charity.
I can just live like a monk, right?
I could take a job at a hamburger joint, right?
And then give all my money away to UNICEF.
Some of that doesn't feel right.
Because I think that, you know,
you know that you have abilities.
And you want to see them flourish.
And you want to, that's why I think,
you shouldn't be flipping hamburgers
and giving the money away.
That's not what you should be doing now.
And instead, it would be learning things
that make it possible
to do good works.
So, I don't know what,
what is the perfect career?
I mean, I mentioned Paul Allen or Bill Gates.
Bill Gates, I shouldn't give you an example
of dropping out of college,
but he dropped out of college.
And by the way, you should do that
if you have a Microsoft-size idea.
But I think I've said this before.
We took,
we took a lot of time to do this.
But,
ألا
I don't know, what is a perfect career?
I'll give you another example.
Muhammad Yunus.
You've heard of him.
He went to a Ph.D.
program at Vanderbilt University, got his
Ph.D. in 1969, became an assistant professor of
economics at Middle Tennessee State University.
But then the big thing that
he did is, he went back to
Bangladesh and founded the Grameen Bank, which specialized
in making microfinance loans in Bangladesh.
And that was in 76.
Grameen apparently means, of the
Vancouver.
It's a village in Bengali.
But what he did is, he
conceived of a new way of
making loans to very low-income people.
Banks before Yunus didn't have much interest in lending to
low-income people, because the costs of administering the
loans seemed to be too high relative to
what you could get back.
But he had a scheme for getting people to
pay back the loans.
Often, they would make loans to
women in groups, impoverished women.
But he would lend to the
whole group and say that the whole
group is jointly liable to the debt.
That's the only way we'll make it.
And it's for business, for starting a business, like
getting a wheeled cart where
you could sell food on the
street, some simple, low business like that.
You can't do it unless you
get a little bit of capital, enough
to buy the cart and buy
the first food to start selling.
And these women can't get that.
They can't.
But when he makes it available
to them as a group, they
then interact with each other and enforce the good behavior
of each other, and it's a system that worked.
So he won the Nobel Peace Prize in 2006.
It was not the prize in
economics, it was the prize in
peace.
So that's an example of the
kind of careers that I think
some of you might think about.
I'm going to go back to the book.
So I think that in
looking forward to your own careers,
you have to think about the next five decades.
You're going to be working.
I said this before, I think.
But you're going to be
working for another 50 years, right?
More, if you enjoy it.
With modern health care, you
might live to 100, but you
won't be working at 100 probably.
You'll probably retire by then.
Maybe not.
Maybe you've got a century ahead of you.
But you're going to be working.
And I think that the world
will change a lot over this
interval of time.
I think that, by the way, information technology will be
changing so many things that we
do in ways that we can't see.
And financial markets will be everywhere.
So I may be presumptuous to
think that some of these ideas
here are likely to come about,
but I've come to start to think
that they're all inevitable.
Because we've already seen the past.
We've seen how financial markets have captured more and
more risks.
And we have such an advance
in our technology that there really
ought to be big changes that will come.
So I guess what you have
to do is maintain a century-long
personal outlook.
I mean, just think about how
much happened in the last three,
four, five, six, seven, eight,
nine, ten years of the last
century.
We had two world wars.
We had the whole communism came and disappeared.
Extreme communism came and disappeared.
Things like that are going
to happen in the next century.
And so, I think you have
to reflect on your role as an
agent, not to think of
it as something that a remote
government is handling.. This is something
that you have responsibility to do.
Thank you.
Thank you, Dr.
Kuhn, for helping develop how the
world will turn out in the
next century.
I was just saying that governments come and go, but
financial contracts and institutions and the people who
manage them continue.
I think that you face
great career risks in this new
environment.
I mentioned before, the 40-year-old who finds that his
career is suddenly eliminated because of a crisis.
He's eliminated because of some random change.
There's evidence that what happens to
you in life depends on random events.
It's really so much unforecastable.
I'm thinking of myself, for example.
What did I think I would be doing?
I'm still, I just stay in the same place.
I've lived in New Haven for almost
30 years, and I've been a college professor.
But when I was your age, I never thought that
I would be doing public speaking the way I have been.
I'm all over the, I don't mean
to exaggerate, but I didn't have the confidence.
I was on my high school debate
team, and I didn't particularly do well.
I think you just develop, careers develop, and
random things happen, and you discover things about yourself.
I was going to point out studies that
show how random events affect where you go.
So, Joshua Angrist, who's an economist, he's a professor at the University
of New York, and he's a professor at the University of New York.
He's a professor at the University of New York.
He did a study of the effect of
the draft lottery on success of people in life.
In 1969, during the Vietnam War, the U.S. government
decided to use a lottery based on birth dates
to decide who gets drafted into
the U.S. Army and sent to Vietnam.
And so, Angrist thought that
was a good, controlled experiment.
Let's compare the lifetime income of people who, the way they
did it is they drew out of an urn all birth dates.
There's 366 days, birth dates.
They drew them out of an urn, and the first one
who was drawn was the first one to go to Vietnam.
And then, as it went down, the lower, the higher the number,
the less likely it is that you would ever be asked to go.
And so, Angrist, by the way, I got 362.
I got 362.
I couldn't believe it.
What great luck.
We were listening on the radio.
I was a graduate student.
We were listening on the radio for the lottery numbers.
And we were drinking beer, and people were
all excited, wondering who was going to get drafted.
And I thought, you know, when it got into the 50,
350, 351, 352, I thought, I must have missed my birthday.
It can't be this far down.
But I got 362.
And that's part of my success story.
Because according to Angrist, people who were drafted, who got the
low number on the lottery, ended up with lower lifetime earnings.
And, you know, that kind of
random event affects your whole life.
You know, the word career goes back to the sense that there are random
things that happen, opportunities that come, and lack of opportunities that hurt your career.
And that hurt your life.
So, I think that you have to
accept the fact that it's a risky world.
That you have to try to position yourself.
Maintain.
I think one important piece of advice I like to
think of is maintain an orientation toward history in the making.
That there's a tendency for people to think of,
to orient themselves in terms of their own life cycle.
What's going on now?
Well, I'm a junior at Yale, and I'm
going to be applying to graduate school next year.
You should be thinking, well, this is a time in
history when, you know, the Middle East is changing rapidly.
That the, you know, the
emerging countries are developing new technologies.
And thinking about the opportunities that
are happening in the Middle East.
And thinking about the opportunities
that are happening in the world.
That's kind of what we got
from Hank Greenberg in his lecture.
Remember that he said that the founder of his company decided
to move to China at the beginning of the 20th century.
And founded a business because of what he saw was
happening in Shanghai, which was an international city at the time.
So, I'm going to go there, and
I'm going to make it a business.
That's kind of positioning yourself with history.
And then he moved out of China.
And then he moved back in.
I mean, this is history awareness.
And I think that it matters enormously.
But you still can't completely eliminate
the role of chance in your life.
This is a time-honored principle.
I was actually going to quote the Bible.
Ecclesiastes was the book of the
Bible written probably, when was that written?
Around 500 B.C. something like that.
600 B.C.
And this is, you've probably heard this.
I returned and saw under the sun, that the race
is not to the swift, nor the battle to the strong,
neither yet bread to the wise, nor yet riches to
men of understanding, nor yet favor to men of skill,
but time and chance happeneth to them all.
So, that's a time-honored truth.
Randomness.
I actually had this, time
and chance happeneth to them all.
I actually had that inscribed in
Latin, when I had my office redone.
It's over my desk in my office at home.
Tempus casumque in omnibus.
Chance plays a huge role in our lives.
And this risky world plays a
sequence of events over your lifetime,
that we have to try to manage.
So, what I hope to do in this
course, this is really a course about managing risks,
as well as enterprise and creating a cooperative spirit.
I wanted to try to convey to
you that we have a technology for that,
that should be a part of your life.
All right. Thank you.